But on the inside, I'm really English, so everybody irritates me. (Laughter) It's true. And the thing is, my family are Arab from Yemen, and I knew that that channel, Bab-el-Mandeb, is not that much of a feat to cross. And I kept asking myself this really simple question: if the ancestors to New World monkeys could somehow cross the Atlantic Ocean, why couldn't humans cross that tiny stretch of water? But the thing is, Yemen, compared to, let's say, Europe, was so understudied that it was something akin to near virgin territory. But that, along with its location, made the sheer potential for discovery so exciting, and I had so many questions. When did we first start using Bab-el-Mandeb? But also, which species of human besides ourselves made it to Yemen? Might we find a species as yet unknown to science? And it turned out, I wasn't the only one who had noticed Yemen's potential. There was actually a few other academics out there. But sadly, due to political instability, they moved out, and so I moved in. And I was looking for caves: caves because caves are the original prime real estate. But also because if you're looking for fossils in that kind of heat, your best bet for fossil preservation is always going to be caves. But then, Yemen took a really sad turn for the worse, and just a few days before I was due to fly out to Yemen, the civil war escalated into a regional conflict, the capital's airport was bombed and Yemen became a no-fly zone.
pero por dentro soy bien inglesa, por eso la gente me irrita. (Risas) Es verdad. Lo cierto es que mi familia árabe procede de Yemen y yo sabía que ese canal, Bab-el-Mandeb, no es tan difícil de cruzar. Siempre me hice esta sencilla pregunta: si los descendientes del mono del Nuevo Mundo cruzaron el Atlántico, ¿por qué no pudieron los humanos cruzar ese diminuto estrecho de agua? Lo que pasa es que Yemen, comparado con Europa, por ejemplo, ha sido tan poco explorado que fue considerado territorio casi virgen. Ese hecho, además de su ubicación, hizo que el potencial para la exploración fuera, precisamente, lo fascinante. Y tenía un montón de preguntas: ¿cuándo se empezó a usar el estrecho de Bab-el-Mandeb y qué especies humanas, además de la nuestra, llegaron a Yemen? ¿Podría existir alguna especie que la ciencia aún no ha descubierto? Pero no fui la única que advirtió el potencial de Yemen. Algunos académicos mostraron interés, pero lamentablemente desistieron por la inestabilidad política, y allí decidí participar yo. Mi propósito era encontrar cuevas. ¿Por qué cuevas? Porque eran los terrenos originales más codiciados. Pero, también, porque si buscamos fósiles en un clima tan cálido, el mejor lugar donde se preservarán siempre será en una cueva. Pero luego, la situación en Yemen se complicó seriamente y, a pocos días de mi vuelo hacia allí, la guerra civil recrudeció y llegó a ser un conflicto en la región. Bombardearon el aeropuerto de la ciudad y se prohibió la circulación aérea sobre Yemen.
Now, my parents made this decision before I was born: that I would be born British.
Ahora bien, mis padres tomaron una decisión antes de mi nacimiento: que yo naciera en Gran Bretaña.
I had nothing to do with the best decision of my life. And now ... Now the lucky ones in my family have escaped, and the others, the others are being been bombed and send you WhatsApp messages that make you detest your very existence. This war's been going on for four years. It's been going on for over four years, and it has led to a humanitarian crisis. There is a famine there, a man-made famine. That's a man-made famine, so not a natural famine, an entirely man-made famine that the UN has warned could be the worst famine the world has seen in a hundred years. This war has made it clear to me more than ever that no place, no people deserve to get left behind. And so I was joining these other teams, and I was forming new collaborations in other unstable places. But I was desperate to get back into Yemen, because for me, Yemen's really personal. And so I kept trying to think of a project I could do in Yemen that would help highlight what was going on there. And every idea I had just kept failing, or it was just too high-risk, because let's be honest, most of Yemen is just too dangerous for a Western team. But then I was told that Socotra, a Yemeni island, was safe once you got there. In fact, it turned out there was a few local and international academics that were still working there. And that got me really excited, because look at Socotra's proximity to Africa. And yet we have no idea when humans arrived on that island. But Socotra, for those of you who know it, well, let's just say you probably know it for a completely different reason. You probably know it as the Galapagos of the Indian Ocean, because it is one of the most biodiverse places on this earth. But we were also getting information that this incredibly delicate environment and its people were under threat because they were at the frontline of both Middle Eastern politics and climate change. And it slowly dawned on me that Socotra was my Yemen project. And so I wanted to put together a huge multidisciplinary team. We wanted to cross the archipelago on foot, camel and dhow boat to conduct a health check of this place.
Yo no tuve participación en la mejor decisión de mi vida. Y ahora... los familiares que tuvieron suerte pudieron escapar, y los otros... los otros sufren bombardeos y envían mensajes por WhatsApp que nos amargan la existencia. Esta guerra lleva ya cuatro años. Son ya cuatro años que causaron una crisis humanitaria. La gente pasa hambre allí, una hambruna causada por el hombre. Causada por el hombre; no es de origen natural. Es pura y exclusivamente causada por el hombre. La ONU advierte que podría ser la peor hambruna de los últimos 100 años. Esta guerra me ha dejado más claro que nunca que ningún lugar, ninguna persona merece ser dejada de lado. Entonces me conecté con otros grupos y empezamos a trabajar en conjunto en otros lugares inestables. Pero yo estaba desesperada por volver a Yemen, porque allí están mis raíces. Y entonces empecé a pensar en algún proyecto para hacer en Yemen que me permitiera mostrar lo que estaba pasando allí. Pero todas mis ideas caían en saco roto, o implicaban un alto riesgo, porque, seamos sinceros, casi todo Yemen es peligroso para quienes vienen de Occidente. Pero luego me enteré de que Socotra, una isla yemení, era un sitio seguro una vez que llegabas allí. De hecho, ya había algunos académicos locales y extranjeros que trabajaban en el lugar. Eso me entusiasmó enormemente, porque observen la proximidad de Socotra con África. Sin embargo, no teníamos idea de cuándo habían llegado los humanos a la isla. Pero para quienes conocen Socotra... Bueno, es posible que la conozcan por una razón totalmente distinta. Quizá la conozcan como la Galápagos del océano Índico, porque es uno de los sitios con mayor biodiversidad del planeta. Pero también nos enteramos de que ese medioambiente tan delicado y sus pobladores estaban bajo amenaza, en una situación crítica, tanto en la política de Medio Oriente como en el cambio climático. Y de a poco fui madurando la idea de que Socotra era mi proyecto en Yemen. Decidí entonces conformar un enorme equipo multidisciplinario. Decidimos cruzar el archipiélago a pie, en camello y en embarcaciones de vela para hacer un control sanitario en la zona.
This has only been attempted once before, and it was in 1999. But the thing is, that is not an easy thing to pull off. And so we desperately needed a recce, and for those of you who aren't familiar with British English, a recce is like a scouting expedition. It's like a reconnaissance. And I often say that a really big expedition without a recce is a bit like a first date without a Facebook stalk. (Laughter) Like, it's doable, but is it wise? There's a few too many knowing laughs in this room. Anyway, so then our recce team thankfully were no strangers to unstable places, which, let's be honest, is kind of important because we were trying to get to a place between Yemen and Somalia, And after calling in what felt like a million favors, including to the deputy governor, we finally found ourselves on the move, albeit on a wooden cement cargo ship sailing through pirate waters in the Indian Ocean with this as a toilet. (Laughter) Can you guys see this? You know how everybody has their worst toilet story? Well, I've never swam with dolphins before. I just went straight to pooping on them. (Laughter) And also, I genuinely discovered that I am genuinely less stressed by pirate waters than I am with a cockroach infestation that was so intense that at one point I went belowdeck, and the floor was black and it was moving. (Audience moans) Yeah, and at night there was three raised platforms to sleep on, but there was only -- let's say there was four team members, and the thing is, if you got a raised platform to sleep on, you only had to contend with a few cockroaches during the night, whereas if you got the floor, good luck to you. And so I was the only girl in the team and the whole ship, so I got away without sleeping on the floor. And then, on, like, the fourth or fifth night,
Se había hecho solo una vez, en 1999. El problema es que organizar esto no era nada fácil. Necesitábamos imperiosamente hacer un reconocimiento de área. Para quienes no lo saben, es como una expedición para reconocer el terreno. Y suelo decir que una expedición de grandes proporciones sin reconocimiento previo es como una primera cita sin antes haber espiado al otro en Facebook. (Risas) Es decir, se puede; pero ¿conviene? Percibo muchas risas cómplices, pero sigamos adelante. Por suerte, el equipo de reconocimiento ya había estado en estos sitios inestables, lo cual, a decir verdad, tenía su importancia porque intentaríamos entrar a un lugar entre Yemen y Somalia. Y luego de pedir lo que pareció un millón de favores, incluyendo al vicegobernador, finalmente nos pusimos en marcha. Eso sí, en un buque de madera que cargaba cemento y atravesaba zonas de piratas en el océano Índico, con este baño. (Risas) ¿Lo ven bien? ¿Saben cuál es la peor experiencia que se puede tener con un baño? Bueno, nunca había nadado con delfines. Directamente les hice caca encima. (Risas) Por otro lado, descubrí que estresa significativamente menos andar entre mares de piratas que estar... en medio de una invasión de cucarachas, tan multitudinaria que, cuando fui a la cubierta inferior, el piso entero era negro, y se movía. (Lamentos de la audiencia) Para dormir, había tres plataformas elevadas para 14 miembros en total. Si dormías en una de esas plataformas, había que soportar solo algunas cucarachas en la noche. Pero si te tocaba el piso, que la suerte te acompañe. Ahora bien, yo era la única mujer del equipo y del barco, así que me salvé de dormir en el piso. Hasta que la cuarta o quinta noche,
Martin Edström looks at me and goes, "Ella, Ella I really believe in equality." (Laughter) So we were sailing on that cement cargo ship for three days, and then we slowly started seeing land. And after three years of failing, I was finally seeing Yemen. And there is no feeling on earth like that start of an expedition. It's this moment where you jump out of a jeep or you look up from a boat and you know that there's this possibility, it's small but it's still there, that you're about to find something that could add to or change our knowledge of who we are and where we come from. There is no feeling like it on earth, and it's a feeling that so many scientists have but rarely in politically unstable places. Because Western scientists are discouraged or all-out barred from working in unstable places. But here's the thing: scientists specialize in the jungle. Scientists work in deep cave systems. Scientists attach themselves to rockets and blow themselves into outer space. But apparently, working in an unstable place is deemed too high-risk. It is completely arbitrary. Who here in this room wasn't brought up on adventure stories? And most of our heroes were actually scientists and academics. Science was about going out into the unknown. It was about truly global exploration, even if there were risks. And so when did it become acceptable to make it difficult for science to happen in unstable places? And look, I'm not saying that all scientists should go off and start working in unstable places. This isn't some gung-ho call. But here's the thing: for those who have done the research, understand security protocol and are trained, stop stopping those who want to. Plus, just because one part of a country is an active war zone doesn't mean the whole country is. I'm not saying we should go into active war zones. But Iraqi Kurdistan looks very different from Fallujah. And actually, a few months after I couldn't get into Yemen, another team adopted me. So Professor Graeme Barker's team were actually working in Iraqi Kurdistan, and they were digging up Shanidar Cave. Now, Shanidar Cave a few decades earlier had unveiled a Neanderthal known as Shanidar 1. Now, for a BBC/PBS TV series we actually brought Shanidar 1 to life, and I want you guys to meet Ned, Ned the Neanderthal. Now here's the coolest thing about Ned. Ned, this guy, you're meeting him before his injuries. See, it turned out that Ned was severely disabled.
Martin Edström me mira y me dice: "Ella, creo firmemente en la igualdad". (Risas) Estuvimos a bordo de ese buque cargado de cemento durante tres días, y luego fuimos divisando la tierra poco a poco. Después de tres años de intentos fallidos, finalmente llegaba a Yemen. No hay sensación más fuerte que empezar una expedición así. Ese momento en que uno salta del 'jeep' o mira desde la embarcación anuncia que existe la posibilidad, remota pero real, de que estás a punto de descubrir algo que puede complementar o cambiar lo que sabemos de nosotros y nuestros orígenes. Esa sensación es absolutamente única, una sensación que tantos científicos tienen, pero casi nunca en sitios políticamente inestables. Porque a los científicos de Occidente se los desalienta, o directamente se les prohíbe, trabajar en lugares inestables. Pero el tema es el siguiente: los científicos trabajan en las selvas, trabajan en sistemas de cuevas profundas, se suben a un cohete y se lanzan al espacio exterior, pero tal parece que trabajar en un sitio inestable se considera de alto riesgo. Es totalmente arbitrario. De los presentes, ¿quién no ha crecido con historias de aventuras? Y la mayoría de nuestros héroes eran, precisamente, científicos y académicos. La ciencia consistía en investigar lo desconocido. Implicaba una exploración del mundo, aunque hubiera riesgos. Por eso, ¿desde cuándo se empezó a aceptar que hacer ciencia es difícil en lugares inestables? Y aclaro: no digo que todos los científicos deban lanzarse a trabajar en sitios inestables. No es un llamado para ir todos a la carga. El asunto es este: a quienes han investigado, conocen los protocolos de seguridad y están capacitados, no los detengan si quieren ir. Además, solo porque una parte del país está involucrada activamente en la guerra no significa que todo el país lo esté. No digo que debamos ir a las zonas que están en guerra. Pero el Kurdistán iraquí es bien distinto a Faluya. De hecho, a pocos meses de mi ingreso frustrado a Yemen, otro equipo me invitó a trabajar. El equipo del profesor Graeme Barker trabajaba en el Kurdistán iraquí, y hacía excavaciones en la cueva de Shanidar. Hace algunas décadas, en esta cueva, se había descubierto un Neandertal al que se llamó "Shanidar 1". Para la serie televisiva de la BBC, generamos la imagen de Shanidar 1. Les presento a Ned. Ned, el Neandertal. Ahora les diré qué es lo fascinante de Ned. A este hombre, Ned, lo ven ahora antes de sus lesiones. Parece ser que Ned tuvo una grave discapacidad.
He was in fact so disabled that there is no way he could have survived without the help of other Neanderthals. And so this was proof that, at least for this population of Neanderthals at this time,
De hecho, tal era esa discapacidad que no hay modo alguno de que haya podido sobrevivir sin la ayuda de otros Neandertales. Esto demuestra que, al menos en esta población de Neandertales de aquella época,
Neanderthals were like us, and they sometimes looked after those who couldn't look after themselves. Ned's an Iraqi Neanderthal. So what else are we missing? What incredible scientific discoveries are we not making because we're not looking? And by the way, these places, they deserve narratives of hope, and science and exploration can be a part of that. In fact, I would argue that it can tangibly aid development, and these discoveries become a huge source of local pride. And that brings me to the second reason why science has a geography problem. See, we don't empower local academics, do we? Like, it's not lost on me that in my particular field of paleoanthropology
los Neandertales eran como nosotros, y a veces cuidaban de quienes no podían cuidarse solos. Pero Ned es un Neandertal iraquí. Me pregunto: ¿qué más nos estamos perdiendo? ¿Qué increíbles descubrimientos no estamos haciendo tan solo porque no estamos buscando? Y, por cierto, estos sitios merecen una historia de esperanzas, y la ciencia y la exploración pueden ser parte de esa historia. Es más, diría que pueden contribuir al desarrollo de manera tangible, y que estos descubrimientos pueden ser una gran fuente de orgullo para el país. Veamos el segundo motivo de por qué la ciencia tiene un problema geográfico. Hay una realidad, y es que no empoderamos a los académicos locales, ¿correcto? Es decir, no pasa desapercibido para mí que, en mi ámbito particular de la paleoantropología,
we study human origins, but we have so few diverse scientists. And the thing is, these places are full of students and academics who are desperate to collaborate, and the truth is that for them, they have fewer security issues than us. I think we constantly forget that for them it's not a hostile environment; for them it's home.
estudiamos los orígenes del ser humano, pero tenemos poquísima diversidad de científicos. Y la realidad es que estos lugares están llenos de alumnos y académicos que están desesperados por colaborar, y lo cierto es que ellos tienen menos recelo que nosotros por el tema de la inseguridad. Olvidamos permanentemente que, para ellos, no es un ambiente hostil. Para ellos, es su patria.
I'm telling you, research done in unstable places with local collaborators can lead to incredible discoveries, and that is what we are hoping upon hope to do in Socotra. They call Socotra the most alien-looking place on earth, and myself, Leon McCarron, Martin Edström and Rhys Thwaites-Jones could see why. I mean, look at this place. These places, they're not hellholes, they're not write-offs, they're the future frontline of science and exploration. 90 percent of the reptiles on this island, 37 percent of the plant species exist here and nowhere else on earth, and that includes this species of dragon's blood tree, which actually bleeds this red resin.
Insisto en que las investigaciones realizadas en sitios inestables con colaboradores del lugar puede llevarnos a descubrimientos increíbles, y deseamos con toda el alma poder hacerlo en Socotra. Se dice que Socotra es el lugar más exótico del planeta. Y con Leon McCarron, Martin Edström y Rhys Thwaites-Jones, lo comprobamos. Vean lo que es este lugar. Estos sitios no son ningún infierno, y no deben ser ignorados. Son el futuro de la ciencia y de la exploración de avanzada. El 90 % de los reptiles que habitan la isla y el 37 % de las especies vegetales existen aquí y en ningún otro lugar, incluyendo este árbol llamado "sangre de dragón", porque produce una resina roja.
And there's something else. People on Socotra, some of them still live in caves, and that is really exciting, because it means if a cave is prime real estate this century, maybe it was a few thousand years ago. But we need the data to prove it, the fossils, the stone tools, and so our scouting team have teamed up with other scientists, anthropologists and storytellers, international as well as local, like Ahmed Alarqbi, and we are desperate to shed a light on this place before it's too late. And now, now we just somehow need to get back for that really big expedition, because science, science has a geography problem. You guys have been a really lovely audience. Thank you. (Applause)
Y hay algo más. Hay gente en Socotra que aún vive en cuevas. Y es muy interesante, porque si, en este siglo, una cueva es una propiedad codiciada, quizá también lo fue hace miles de años. Pero necesitamos datos para probarlo: los fósiles, las herramientas de piedra. Por eso, nuestro equipo explorador se unió a otros científicos, antropólogos y conocedores de la historia, tanto locales como internacionales, como Ahmed Alarqbi, y estamos ansiosos por arrojar luz sobre este sitio antes de que sea demasiado tarde. Y ahora... Ahora, de alguna manera, tenemos que volver para hacer esa gran expedición, porque la ciencia... la ciencia tiene un problema geográfico. Les agradezco por escucharme. Gracias. (Aplausos)